



manueljbo@gmail.com



(+31) 6 822 997 63



live: manueljboliveira

#### **WEBPAGES**





linkedin.com/in/manueljbo



**GitHub** github.com/olivethree



@manueliho

Institutional

williamjamescr.org/peo ple/manuel-oliveira/

## MANUEL J. BARBOSA DE OLIVEIRA

I'm a behavioral scientist with scientific training in advanced statistics, programming, and Psychology.

I earned my Ph.D. degree after spending almost 5 years conducting research at the William James Center for Research and Utrecht University. This work resulted in the publication of multiple articles on high impact scientific journals, which offered important contributions to the fields of face and personality perception. Over the past years, I became passionate about programming and data analysis. I'm continuously seeking to learn and develop myself both professionally and personally. My ambition is to collaborate and bring value to the development of new applications and data products that optimize services, workflows, or make people's lives easier in general.

#### **SKILLS**

#### **Programming languages & Tools**

- ✓ R: base, tidyverse, renv
- ✓ Python: pandas, django, flask, scikit-learn, tkinter, pyqt5
- √ Web development languages: HTML, CSS (basic), JavaScript (basic)
- ✓ SQL: SQLite, PostgreSQL
- ✓ Version control: Git, GitHub
- √ bash, conda, homebrew
- ✓ Docker (basic)
- ✓ Web hosting and server setup basics (Linode, AWS EC2)
- √ Google Analytics
- ✓ Statistics software: SPSS, Statistica, Jamovi
- ✓ Experiment building tools: PsychoPy, E-Prime, Qualtrics
- ✓ Face manipulation tools: FaceGen, Psychomorph, Fantamorph
- ✓ Other tools: GIMP, Inkscape

### **Data Analysis**

- ✓ General Linear Models:
  - ✓ General ANOVA models
  - ✓ Linear Regression
  - ✓ Logistic Regression
  - ✓ Linear Mixed-Effects Models | HLMs
  - ✓ Path analysis and SEM (basics)
- ✓ Dimensionality Reduction: PCA, FA, MDS, Cluster Analysis, Autoenconders (Deep Learning)
- ✓ Signal Detection Theory Analysis
- ✓ Experience with psychophysical image classification methods
- ✓ Pixel data analysis
- ✓ Machine Learning & Deep Learning (basic knowledge)

**LANGUAGES** 

English Portuguese

## **REFERENCES**

Upon request.

## MANUEL J. BARBOSA DE OLIVEIRA

#### **EXPERIENCE**

01/2020 - Present

#### Freelancer

Data Analysis | Python app development | Scientific Writing

02/2015 - 12/2019

#### PhD Candidate

ISPA – Instituto Universitário, William James Center for Research & Utrecht University

2015 - 2019

### **Tutoring in Research Skills**

ISPA – Instituto Universitário (12.5 hours total)

2013 - 2018

#### **Teaching Assistant**

11-12/2017 | ISPA - Instituto Universitário

- Full lectures: Stereotypes; Impression Formation; Trait Inferences (9 hours total) 10/2013 & 10/2014 | University of Lisbon
- Software tools for face perception research module (4 hours total)

2012 - 2015

#### **Research Assistant**

11/2014 - 01/2015 | Faculty of Psychology, University of Lisbon 05/2014 - 08/2014 | ISCTE – IUL

09/2013 – 10/2013 | Duke University (remote)

- Project coordinated by Prof. Dan Ariely & Ximena Garcia-Rada (Mann et al., 2016)
   07/2012 01/2014 | Faculty of Psychology, University of Lisbon
- Project: "The Paradox of Stereotypes and other Beliefs: Resistant, Self-perpetuating but Context-dependent – Exploring a New Model"

2010 – 2011

#### **Strategic Planner**

Internship at Publicis Advertising, Lisbon Department

### **EDUCATION**

2015 - 2019

### Ph.D. Social Psychology

ISPA – Instituto Universitário, William James Center for Research | 2 years Utrecht University | 2 years

Graduated summa cum laude (with Praise and Distinction)

Advisers: Teresa Garcia-Marques, Ph.D., ISPA-Instituto Universitário, WJCR

Leonel Garcia-Marques, Ph.D., Universidade de Lisboa

Ron Dotsch, Ph.D., Utrecht University

Thesis: "The structuring role of valence in the relationship between and

within models of face and trait impressions"

2009 - 2011

## M.Sc. Social and Organizational Psychology

ISPA - Instituto Universitário

ECTS: A | GPA: 3.29/4.00

Adviser: Teresa Garcia-Marques, Ph.D.

Thesis topic: Implicit versus explicit evaluations of facial maturity

2006 - 2009

B.Sc. Psychology

University of Aveiro

ECTS: A | GPA: 3.36/4.00







# **MANUEL J. BARBOSA DE OLIVEIRA**

### **PUBLICATIONS**

- Oliveira, M., Garcia-Marques, T., Garcia-Marques, L., & Dotsch, R. (2020). Good to bad or bad to bad? What is the relationship between valence and the trait content of the Big Two? *European Journal of Social Psychology*, 50(2), 463-483. doi: 10.1002/ejsp.2618
- **Oliveira, M.**, Garcia-Marques, T., & Dotsch, R. (2019). Combining traits into a face: A reverse correlation approach. *Social Cognition*, *37*(5), 516-545. doi: 10.1521/soco.2019.37.5.516
- Oliveira, M., Garcia-Marques, T., Dotsch, R., & Garcia-Marques, L. (2019).

  Dominance and competence face to face: Dissociations obtained with a reverse correlation approach. *European Journal of Social Psychology, 49*(5), 888-902. doi: 10.1002/ejsp.2569
- Santos, A., Almeida, F., Palma, T., **Oliveira, M.**, & Garcia-Marques, L. (2017). The cultural stereotype of professional groups: Consensus, accessibility and typicality of stereotypic contents. *Análise Psicológica*, *35*, 557-568. doi: <a href="https://doi.org/10.14417/ap.1385">10.14417/ap.1385</a>
- Ramos, T., **Oliveira, M.**, Santos, A. S., Garcia-Marques, & L. Carneiro, P. (2016). Evaluating young and old faces on social dimensions: Trustworthiness and dominance. *Psicológica*, *37*(2), 169-185. Retrieved from <a href="https://www.uv.es/psicologica/articulos2.16/4Ramos.pdf">https://www.uv.es/psicologica/articulos2.16/4Ramos.pdf</a>
- Oliveira, M., & Miranda, M. (2012). Paradigma: Teste de associação implícita [Paradigm: Implicit association test]. *Laboratório de Psicologia*, *10*, 235-249. doi: 10.14417/lp.673